<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Equineist Blog</title>
    <link>https://equineist.com/blog</link>
    <description>Thoughts on horse riding, equine therapy, and the human-horse bond.</description>
    
    <item>
      <title>"Why and How to Keep Your Horse’s Shoes Clean: A Complete Guide"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/why-and-how-to-keep-your-horses-shoes-clean-a-complete-guide</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  As a dedicated horse owner, you know that every aspect of equine care is crucial. However, one often overlooked element is the cleanliness of your horse's shoes and hooves.    Neglecting this vital task can lead to a host of problems, from minor discomfort to severe health issues.  In this compreh]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/why-and-how-to-keep-your-horses-shoes-clean-a-complete-guide</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"What is Saddle Fitting? What New Equestrians Should Know"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/what-is-saddle-fitting-what-new-equestrians-should-know</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Saddle fitting is a crucial aspect of horseback riding that every equestrian, especially beginners, should understand thoroughly.
   It's the meticulous process of ensuring that a saddle provides optimal comfort and safety for both the horse and rider.      A well-fitted saddle is not just about c]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/what-is-saddle-fitting-what-new-equestrians-should-know</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"The Importance of Lunging Your Horse: 10 Reasons to Make It a Regular Practice"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/the-importance-of-lunging-your-horse-10-reasons-to-make-it-a-regular-practice</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Lunging is a vital exercise that offers numerous benefits for both horse and handler. It involves guiding the horse in a controlled circle using a long line and specific commands.     Far from being a simple task, lunging plays a crucial role in maintaining your horse's physical fitness, mental fo]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/the-importance-of-lunging-your-horse-10-reasons-to-make-it-a-regular-practice</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"Rahvan Horses: A Glimpse into Their Origin, Features, and Global Presence"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/rahvan-horses-a-glimpse-into-their-origin-features-and-global-presence</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Rahvan horses, a breed deeply rooted in the traditions and cultures of the regions they hail from, are a symbol of endurance, agility, and speed.    Known for their unique gait and resilience, these horses have played a vital role in the lives of the people who have bred and raised them for centur]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/rahvan-horses-a-glimpse-into-their-origin-features-and-global-presence</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"Mastering Horse Ground Exercises: The Key to a Trustworthy and Confident Horse"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/mastering-horse-ground-exercises-the-key-to-a-trustworthy-and-confident-horse</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Ground exercises are an important aspect of horse training. These activities take place on the ground and help create a strong bond between horse and handler.     They build trust, respect, and communication, all of which are crucial for any horse, whether it's young, experienced, or just beginnin]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/mastering-horse-ground-exercises-the-key-to-a-trustworthy-and-confident-horse</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"How Often Should You Trim Your Horse's Shoes, and Why It’s Important"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/how-often-should-you-trim-your-horses-shoes-and-why-its-important</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Maintaining your horse's hooves through regular trimming is a crucial aspect of equine care.  
   This practice not only ensures your horse's health and comfort but also significantly impacts their overall performance and longevity.    Generally, horses require hoof trimming every 4 to 8 weeks, th]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/how-often-should-you-trim-your-horses-shoes-and-why-its-important</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"How Often Should You Exercise Your Horse, and Why It’s Important?"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/how-often-should-you-exercise-your-horse-and-why-its-important</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Maintaining a consistent exercise regimen for your horse is not merely beneficial—it's absolutely essential for their overall well-being.  Horses are inherently energetic creatures, evolved for constant movement across vast plains.     When deprived of regular physical activity, they can succumb t]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/how-often-should-you-exercise-your-horse-and-why-its-important</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"Horse Vital Signs: What You Should Know as a Horse Owner and Why Monitoring is Crucial"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/horse-vital-signs-what-you-should-know-as-a-horse-owner-and-why-monitoring-is-crucial</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Monitoring your horse's vital signs is crucial for their health and well-being. By knowing what's normal, you can spot problems early and act fast. Here's what to watch:  ### 1. Temperature  Normal range: 99°F to 101.5°F (37.2°C to 38.6°C). Check it with a livestock thermometer. Fever? Could be in]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/horse-vital-signs-what-you-should-know-as-a-horse-owner-and-why-monitoring-is-crucial</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"Horse Laminitis: The First Nightmare Every Horse Owner Should Fear"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/horse-laminitis-the-first-nightmare-every-horse-owner-should-fear</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Laminitis, a condition that strikes fear into the hearts of horse-owners worldwide, demands our utmost attention and understanding.     This guide delves into the intricacies of laminitis, offering insights and practical advice to help you safeguard your equine companion's well-being.  ### Underst]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/horse-laminitis-the-first-nightmare-every-horse-owner-should-fear</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"A Comprehensive Deworming Plan for Your Horses: What You Need to Know"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/a-comprehensive-deworming-plan-for-your-horses-what-you-need-to-know</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Maintaining your horse's health requires a well-planned deworming approach. Unchecked worms and parasites can cause serious health issues, from weight loss to colic and even death in severe cases.     Understanding common horse parasites, available deworming agents, and proper precautions is cruci]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/a-comprehensive-deworming-plan-for-your-horses-what-you-need-to-know</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"What is a Horse?"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-what-is-a-horse</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  What is a horse?  It’s not just a beast of burden. Not just a pet. Not just a vehicle for recreation.  A horse, in its true essence, is a complex, intelligent, and deeply social being, a creature forged by millennia of evolution, history, and partnership with humans. To see a horse as anything les]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-what-is-a-horse</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"What Is a Horse? The Scientific & Philosophical Truths We Must Understand"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-understanding-a-horse</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[   Let me ask you something. When you get on a horse, what do you *really* see?  Is it just an animal? A big pet? A machine built to carry you around?  Or do you see something deeper? Something complex, intelligent, and alive with emotion?  Because if you don’t understand what a horse truly is, biol]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-understanding-a-horse</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"The Rider’s Dilemma: Why You Should Never Ride a Horse That’s Not Right for You"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-riders-dilemma</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[    Let me be brutally honest. I’ve seen it all. Not just the beautiful moments, the sunrise rides, the quiet trust in a horse’s eyes, the way your heart syncs with their rhythm. I’ve also seen the ugly side of riding. The kind that makes you want to turn away, shake your head, and whisper, *“How ca]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-riders-dilemma</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"A Doctor’s View: The Physical and Mental Health Benefits of Working with Horses"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-oct-horse-therapy</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  I started as a doctor. Not because I wanted to be one. But because I had to.  Restless leg syndrome. Epilepsy. Chronic pain. My body was a battlefield. And the medicine? It helped, sure. But it didn’t fix the root. Not really.  Then came Kuzey.  Not by choice. I didn’t plan to become a horse owner]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-oct-horse-therapy</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"Horses Are Not Machines: Why Force and Fear Destroy Trust"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-oct-17-horse-not-a-machine</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  ****  Let me be brutally honest. I’ve seen it all.  Not just the beautiful moments, the sunrise rides, the quiet trust in a horse’s eyes, the way your heart syncs with their rhythm. I’ve also seen the ugly side of riding. The kind that makes you want to turn away, shake your head, and whisper, *“H]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-oct-17-horse-not-a-machine</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"The Purpose Behind Every Ride; Why do we ride! Avoid Mindless Riding Trips!"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-10-riding-with-purpose</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[   We ride because we need to. Not because it’s trendy, not because we want to show off on social media, and certainly not to stroke our own ego.  Before I even touch Kuzey’s bridle, I ask myself: *Why am I riding today?*  This isn’t a formality. It’s the foundation of everything.  ## What I have se]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-10-riding-with-purpose</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"The Hidden Cost of Ignorance: Why Bad Riding Lessons Can Kill Horses and Hurt People"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/25-0ct-18-bad-riding</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[   Let me be brutally honest. I’ve seen it all.    Not just the beautiful moments, the sunrise rides, the quiet trust in a horse’s eyes, the way your heart syncs with their rhythm. I’ve also seen the ugly side of riding. The kind that makes you want to turn away, shake your head, and whisper, *“How ]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/25-0ct-18-bad-riding</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"10 Reasons Why Grooming Is Essential for Your Horse and Why You Should Care"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/10-reasons-why-grooming-is-essential-forhorse-caree-and-why-you-should-care</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[  Grooming is one of the most important aspects of horse care. It goes beyond just making your horse look good; it's an essential part of their health, comfort, and overall well-being.    If you own a horse, you should know that grooming isn't optional. It's something you need to take seriously.  He]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/10-reasons-why-grooming-is-essential-for-your-horse-and-why-you-should-care</guid>
    </item>
  
    <item>
      <title>"10 Most Strange and Beautiful Horse Breeds"</title>
      <link>https://equineist.com/blog/10-most-strange-and-beautiful-horse-breeds</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[     Prepare to embark on a journey through the equine world's most extraordinary breeds. From metallic-coated steeds to curly-haired companions, these 10 Strange Horse Breeds defy conventional expectations.    Centuries of selective breeding have sculpted these magnificent creatures, each with a un]]></description>
      <guid>https://equineist.com/blog/10-most-strange-and-beautiful-horse-breeds</guid>
    </item>
  
  </channel>
</rss>
